嘿，大家好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么上次我们讨论了数学，已经开始接触数学
so last time we talked about maths, and we started getting into maths
以及所有以后会涉及到与数学相关的话题
and all the math like topics that will come in the future
在这个OpenGL系列教程和你们的图形编程之旅中
in this OpenGL series and in your graphics programming journey
今天我们将特别关注其中的一小部分，也就是投影矩阵
today we're going to be specifically focusing on one small part of that, which is projection
投影矩阵是我们需要处理的最大的实际问题之一
projection is one of the biggest actual things that we need to solve
当涉及到在屏幕上渲染图形时，它就是变换管道的一部分
when it comes to rendering graphics on the screen, is part of the transformation pipeline
我们将在接下来的几周里继续探讨这些
which we will continue to explore over the coming weeks
但今天我只想重点讲投影矩阵，这一期不会很长
but today I just want to focus on projection, and this is not going to be a super long episode
因为我不想把这个东西复杂化，让你们摸不着头脑
because I don't want to overcomplicate this for you, and have you scratching your head
我们不打算讨论太多关于数学原理的技术细节
we're not going to talk too much about the technical details on how the maths works
因为对99%的例子来说，这是完全相关的
because that is completely relevant, for 99% of cases
我知道你们很多人可能对它的原理感兴趣
I know they're probably a bunch of you interested in how it actually works
这样你们就能从头开始写你们自己版本的OpenGL
so that you can kind of write your own version of OpenGL from scratch or something
我们以后可能会讲到那个
we might cover that in the future
但今天实际上讲投影矩阵和OpenGL是怎么运行的
but today practically speaking what is projection and OpenGL how does it work
以及我们为什么要用它，所以简单地说，投影矩阵只是
and why do we use it, so to put it simply, projection is just
我们如何得到3D或2D世界中的任意坐标系统
how we go from having some kind of arbitrary coordinate system in our 3D world or 2D world
没关系，我的意思是2D世界就是3D世界，不管怎样，就OpenGL而言
doesn't matter, I mean 2D worlds are really 3D, anyway, as far as looking OpenGL is concerned
这就是我们如何从空间中的坐标或顶点位置开始
it's how we go from having coordinates or vertex positions in that space
以某种方式将它们映射到我们的窗口
to being able to somehow map them to our window
我们在电脑屏幕上渲染的地方
where we're actually rendering on our computer screen
所以我们要把它们投射到这个表面上
so we have to project them somehow onto this to surface
你们可能会有一个巨大的3D世界，有山丘、地形和角色等等
you might have this massive 3D world, with hills and terrain and characters and all of that
最后也很明显，这些山只是一堆三角形
which in the end obviously just hills down to a bunch of triangles
就是由顶点位置组成的
which are made up of vertex positions
但最终3D世界必须以某种方式出现在我们的2D显示器和窗口中
but in the end that 3D world has to somehow be rambled onto our 2D monitor and into our window
那就是投影矩阵
that is what projection is
它本质上是一种数学，将空间中的所有3D点
it is essentially the maths that converts all of those 3D points in space
转换成2D窗口中的东西
into something that is in a 2D kind of window
这就是投影矩阵，所以忘掉所有你们的知道关于投影矩阵的知识吧
that is what projection is, so forget everything you know about projection or whatever
就是这样，就是那么简单，那么转换成位置是什么意思
that's all it is, it is as simple as that, now what do I mean by convert into positions
投影矩阵的实际变换是什么意思
what does that even mean the actual transformation that happens with a projection matrix
我们在上次的数学视频中已经讲过了
which we kind of talked about last time in a math video
我们今天也会讲到
and we will touch on today as well
就是我们把所有那些位置，转换成所谓的标准设备坐标
is we just convert all of those positions that we have into something called normalized device coordinates
也就是某种标准化的空间，然后映射到我们的窗口
which is basically some kind of normalized space that we can, then map to our window
标准空间意味着在每个xyz轴上都有一个-1和1之间的坐标系统
now a normalized space means that literally a coordinate system between -1 and 1 in every axis x y and z
对吧，所以我想说的是，一个窗口的图像分辨率在点上无关紧要
right, so what I'm saying is, the picture that you have a window does not resolution does not matter at this
对吧，不管你们的窗口有多大
right, doesn't matter what size your window is
我们只知道我们的左边窗口，让我们看看，我们在雨滴屏中
all that we know is that the left side of our window, let's just see, we're in rainfall screen
那么左边是-1，右边是1，下面是-1，上面是1
so the left side will be -1, the right side will be 1, the bottom will be -1 and the top will be 1
在这一点上，我们不用太担心z轴，因为它不像x和y那样重要
let's not worry too much about z at this point, because that's not as important to visualize as x and y
所以就是那样，我们有了电脑显示器，我们打开了窗口
so that's it, we have our computer monitor, we have our window open
我们实际渲染所有的图形，在-1和1之间
where we're actually rendering all of our graphics, and that is between -1 and 1
那就是我们需要的所有顶点位置所在的空间
that is how we, that is the space that we need to have all of our vertex positions in
这样我们就可以开始在屏幕上绘制东西
so that we can actually start cauterizing stuff onto the screen
但是我们拥有的是3D世界，或者屏幕上的2D对象
however what we have is like this 3D world, or maybe this 2D object somewhere in our screen
我们需要把它转换到那个空间，那就是投影矩阵的作用
and we need to convert it into that space, that's what a projection matrix does
并且事实上，直到上一期，我们还没有用到投影矩阵
and in fact, up until really last episode, we've just we have not been using a projection matrix
这就是为什么你们可能听到我说空间在-1和1之间
which is why you probably heard me say that our space is between -1 and 1
换句话说，当我们在纹理视频中制作ChernoLogo作为一个例子
in other words, when we actually made that ChernoLogo in the textures video as an example
我们绘制了那个几何图形，就像我们那儿实际使用的顶点位置一样
we plotted that geometry, like the vertex positions that we actually used there
一定在-1和1之间
had to be between a -1 and 1
我想我写的是-0.5或0.5之类的
and I think I wrote something like -0.5 and 0.5 or something like that
因为没有投影矩阵，我们就没有
because without a projection matrix, we have nothing to
我们没有一个实际的矩阵
we don't have an actual matrix
来将顶点位置转换成标准设备坐标空间
to convert our vertex positions into that normalized device kind of coordinate space
所以我们必须一开始就提供，因为如果我们不提供
so we have to provide it initially, because if we don't
如果我们在那个坐标空间之外
if we're going to be well outside of that coordinate space
那么屏幕上就什么都看不到了
then we're not going to see anything on the screen
因为就屏幕而言
because as far as the screen is concerned
也就是在窗口中渲染的内容
as far as what actually gets rendered onto our window
它必须在-1和1之间
that has to be between -1 and 1, it has to be
但这对我们来说有点难处理，它总是-1到1
but it's a bit difficult for us to deal with something, that's just constantly -1 to 1
我的意思是举个例子，假设我们正在渲染一个正方形
I mean as an example, let's just say we're rendering a square
但我们的窗口不是正方形的，它是4×3或16x9
but our window is not square, it's 4 by 3 or it's 16 by 9
我们不能，我的意思是，理论上我们可以做所有的映射
we can't just, I mean we could theoretically do all the maps
每次我们计算顶点位置的时候，我想每次都在做映射
every time we calculate vertex positions, and I guess keep doing the maps every time
这样我们就得到了一个正方形，但是这样不是更简单吗
so that we do get a square, but wouldn't it be easier to just kind of be able to say
好了，那么屏幕的左边呢，也许是0，屏幕的右边就是宽度
okay, well, how about the left side of our screen, maybe is 0, the right side of our screen is width
也许我的窗口是1280x720，假设左边是0，右边就是1280
so maybe my window is 1280 by 720, so let's just say that the left side is 0, right side is 1280
我可以渲染在这之间的任何地方
I can render anywhere in between there
之后我们再考虑将其转化为-1到1的数学问题
and then we'll worry about the maths of actually converting that into -1 to 1 later
所以那就是投影矩阵的作用
so that is essentially what a projection can do for you
它让你们决定你们的坐标空间是什么，这样你们就可以渲染对象
it lets you decide what your coordinate space is, so that you can render objects
不管你们喜欢它们是在空间内，还是在屏幕外
however you like whether they be inside the space, maybe they are outside of the screen
因为我们要处理的是某种相机系统，它只能部分地显示场景
because we're dealing with some kind of camera system, that only shows the scene partially
那就是一个投影矩阵，让我们来做这些，对于3D，这是特别重要的
that's a projection, let's do all that, and for 3D, it's especially important
因为如果你们想一下3D场景是什么样的
because if you think about what a 3D scene looks like
它不像把投影矩阵从-1转换成1那么简单
it's not just as simple as kind of converting your projection from -1 to 1
和狼一样，将它从一个值，从一个大的值，缩放到-1到1
and like wolf, scaling it rather, from a value, from a large kind of value, into -1 to 1
我刚才举的从0到1280的例子就是我的投影矩阵
so as that example that I just gave from 0 to 1280 is my kind of projection matrix
我把那个缩小成-1到1
I'm scaling that down into something that is -1 to 1
你们可能会觉得那很简单，你们知道的
that's might seem to you like oh that's easy, you know
我把它除以1280然后再乘以2或者减去1什么之类的
I'll just divide this by like 1280 and like multiply but two or whatever subtract 1
你们知道的，简单，右边就好了
you know, easy, right done
但是如果你们考虑一个透视投影
but if you think about a perspective projection
这是在3D世界中通常使用的
which is what to is typically use in a 3D world
如果你们只是拍一张某物的照片，看一看物体
if you just take a photo of something, and you take a look at objects
距离更远的物体会变小，比照片上的要小，对吧
objects that are further away actually become smaller, that'd be smaller than the photograph, right
甚至不需要拍照，你们可以用自己的眼睛看
and you don't even have to take a photo for this, you can just look with your own eyes
你们可以看到，嗯，你们知道我可以
and you can see, huh that you know I can
你们知道，那边的山离这里只有这么大
that you know, mountain over there is really just this big from here
因为那就是透视的原理
because of the way that perspective works
因为越远的物体看起来越小
because objects that are further away tend to look smaller
那也是一个需要应用的实际投影
that is also a an actual projection that needs to be applied
如果你们正在处理的是3D场景，那就是投影矩阵的作用
if you're dealing with a 3D scene, and that's what a projection matrix can do
它会观察z的值，然后说好吧，有较大z值的对象
it will essentially look at the z value and say okay, well objects with a larger z value
如果你们用一个正z的坐标系，就像这些物体
if you use a coordinate system where positive z is like far those objects
或者那些z值较低或z值较高的顶点
or those vertices with a lower with a higher z value
最终会更靠近镜头中间
will actually end up being closer to the middle of the camera
会让它们变小，所以那也很重要
which essentially will just make them smaller, so that's really important as well
当我们讲到3D的时候，你们就会发现，透视投影是多么的重要
and when we get into 3D these stuff, you'll see, how important a perspective projection is
但不管怎样，如果我们看一下我准备的这个幻灯片
but anyway, if we just take a look at this little powerpoint slide that I prepared here
我们这里有两种主要的投影类型
we have two different main types of projection here
我们有正交投影和透视投影
we have orthographic projection and perspective projection
所以正交投影通常用于2D渲染，当我说“通常”时，请记住
so orthographic projection is usually used for 2D rendering, now when I say usually, keep in mind
首先，虽然正交投影通常用于2D，但它并不总是用于2D
first of all, while orthographic is usually used for 2D, it's not always used for 2D
在3D中使用正交投影是完全可以的，这实际上是很常见的
it's totally fine to use orthographic for 3D, that's actually done quite commonly
因为它呈现了一个稍微不同的视图
because it presents a slightly different view
这可能对关卡编辑器或3D建模程序等有用
that might be useful for something, like a level editor or a 3D modeling program
透视投影通常用于3D，但我的意思是所有东西都是3D的
perspectives usually use for 3D, but I mean everything is 3D anyway
因为这里有z的概念
because there is the concept of z
所以如果你们考虑的是2D平台游戏
so if you're thinking of a 2D platformer
那实际上可能是使用透视投影，因为可能还有更远的元素
that might actually be using a perspective projection, because there might be elements further away
比如《雷曼兄弟》这款新游戏
if you look at a game such as Rayman, like the new Rayman games
他们有深度的概念
they have that concept of depth
即使你们只能在一个2D平面上移动一个2D轴
even though you can really only move on what is mostly kind of a 2D plane a 2D axis
所以不要把这些当做
so don't take these as like
好吧，透视投影只用于3D，正交投影只用于2D，那是错的
okay, perspective 3D, orthographic 2D, not true
它可以在两种情况下使用，但通常当我们想到正交投影时
it can be used in both cases, but usually when we think of an orthographic projection
我们会想到渲染UI(用户界面)，或者2D游戏之类的东西
we think of rendering something like UI, or something maybe a 2D game or something like that
然而，当我们想到透视投影时，我们想到的是第一视角
whereas when we think, when we think of perspective, we think of like a first person shooter
或者类似的东西，在那里我们实际上有一个我们正在渲染的3D世界
or something like that, where we actually have a 3D world that we're rendering
但那并不是它们的全部用途
but that's not necessarily all they used for
不管怎样，对于这个正交投影，我们会说
anyway, what we'd say over here with this orthographic projection
就是离得越远的物体实际上
is that objects to the further away are not actually
它们不会像透视那样变得更小
they don't get smaller like they do with perspective
你们可以看到这些立方体，它们看起来离得更远
you can see these cubes, they look like they're further away
因为它们更小，我们的眼睛已经习惯了那个
because they're smaller and our eyes are used to that
因为那就是我们在现实世界中看到的
because that's how we see in the real world
而这两个立方体，它们的距离是一样的
whereas these two cubes here, they're the same distance
我的意思是，从所有的意图和目的来看，你们在这两张图中看到了什么
I mean for all intents and purposes, what you see in these two diagrams
我用了5秒的时间做了一个幻灯片，用的是形状
that I just literally made in 5 seconds and powerpoint using the shapes thing
总之，它们提供的是更远的东西
anyway, they're offering these things that are further away
它们的顶点位置和这里的一样
they have the same vertex positions as these ones here
只是这些用的是正交投影，这些都是用透视投影
it's just that these are using orthographic projection, and these are using perspective projection
因为你们知道的
because you know
这些立方体确实有相同的宽度，相同的高度，相同的深度
these cubes do have the same width, the same height, the same depth
所有这些，对吧
all of that, right
它们刚好在一个更远的z值上，而透视投影
they just happen to be at a further z value, and the perspective projection maths that
实际上，当我们用投影矩阵乘以这些顶点时
actually goes on, when we multiply these vertices with our projection matrix
那就是它们变小的原因，因为它们的z值很高
that is what makes them smaller, because they have a high z value
但归根结底
but at the end of the day
所有这些立方体中的每一个顶点位置都会映射到-1到1之间的空间中
every single vertex position of all of these cubes gets mapped into a space that is between -1 and 1
那就是标准设备坐标
and that's what the normalized device coordinates are
这就是在-1和1之间的空间，任何超出这个范围的东西
there are space that are between kind of -1 and 1, anything that is outside of that
那么举个例子，如果我有一个顶点，它最终计算出来是-2
so for example, if I have a vertex, that ends up being calculated to be -2
它不会被渲染
that does not get rendered
它会变得不易发现，因为它在我们的视图之外，超出了我们的视野
it gets cold, because it's outside of our actual view, it's outside of our frosting
现在我们肯定会讨论更多关于，你们是知道的
now we're definitely going to talk more about, you know
当我们开始使用这些投影时
these projections as we start to use them
但让我们在代码中看看它们
but let's take a look at them in our code base
如果我回到这里的OpenGL代码，我有我创建的这个投影矩阵
if I go back to my OpenGL code over here, I have this projection matrix that I'm creating
那么我在这里看到的是一个正交投影
so what I'm doing here is I'm seeing I have an orthographic projection
x的-2到2，y的-1.5到1.5，这就是表示远近的z
between -2 and 2 in x, and -1.5 and 1.5 in y, and then this is just the z the near far
所以我们现在不太担心这个，我渲染的任何东西，任何顶点位置
so we're not going to worry too much about that for now, anything that I render, any vertex position
这些是顶点位置
these are my vertex positions
任何在这个范围之外的顶点位置，这些绑定的都不会出现
any vertex position that lies outside of this, these bounds will not appear
因为这是最左边的x界，这是最右边的x界
because this is the left most x bound, this is the right most x bound
即使我调整这些x坐标，比如-2.5或5或100
so if I was to adjust any of these x coordinates to be say -2.5 or 5 or 100
它们实际也不会渲染
they're not actually going to render
因为那是我的视图，那是我所看到的一切，归根结底
because that is my view, that is all that I see, and at the end of the day
这个正交投影与这些顶点的位置相乘
this orthographic projection when multiplied with these vertex positions
将它们转换成-1到1的空间
is going to convert them to be in that -1 to 1 space
那么举个例子，既然我们选了-2到2
so as an example, since we have chosen -2 to 2
那意味着0实际上是屏幕的中心
that means that 0 is in fact the center the middle of our actual screen
如果我有一个-0.5的顶点，你们可以从中间判断出来
if I have a vertex of -0.5, you can tell that that's kind of from the middle
它在最左边边界的1/4处
it's a quarter of the way towards the left most bound
因为0.5是2的1/4
because 0.5 is a quarter of 2
那么因为这个正交矩阵将把这个位置转换成-1和1之间的位置
so since this orthographic matrix is going to convert this position to be between -1 and 1
然后0和-1之间的1/4是0.25，我们可以通过目测知道
then what is a quarter between 0 and -1, it's 0.25, so we can just tell just by eyeballing this
因为这个投影矩阵很简单
because this projection matrix is so simple
在实际屏幕上这个会变成0.25，如果我们按f5
that this will become 0.25 on our actual screen, and if we do hit f5
这就有点难说了
it'll be a little bit hard to tell
因为我相信我们实际上是在渲染一个部分透明的纹理
because I believe we are actually rendering a texture which is like partially transparent in fact
我要把它删掉，如果我去我的着色器
yeah I'm just gonna get rid of that, if I go to my shader
我要让它，这样我们输出而不是输出纹理颜色
I'm just going to make it, so that we output instead of outputting the texture color
我们只输出白色，所以就是vec4(1.0)，如果我们现在看这个
we're just gonna output white, so just vec4(1.0), and if we look at this now
你们就可以看到，如果目测一下这个
you can see that, if you kind of eyeball this
你们就会知道这是屏幕的中心
you know this is the center of the screen here
这条从正方形开始的最左边的边是向左的1/4
and this left most kind of edge that we have from our square is a quarter of the way to the left
因为它变成了0.25，这里是-0.25，这里是-1
because it becomes 0.25, where this or -0.25, where this is -1
希望你们能理解这块
hopefully this mess is kind of making sense to you
我并不想深入研究，开始绘制图表之类的
I don't really want to dive in, and start drawing diagrams or anything
因为在实践中，注意它并不是很有用
because it's not really that useful to notice in practice
你们只需要知道投影矩阵的作用是什么
you just have to know that what the projection matrix does is
它把它转换成-1到1的正常设备坐标空间，这就是发生的一切
it converts it into that normal device coordinate space of -1 to 1, that's really all that's happening
这只是一个简单的数学运算，投影矩阵没什么好想象的
it's just a simple maths operation, there's nothing to fancy about projection matrixes
到这里，我要做的是在我的Application中
if we go over here, and what I'm actually going to do is, in my Application
我不把它画成640x480，我把它转换成960x540
I'm going to instead of drawing it at 640 by 480, what I convert this to be 960 by 540
现在我要做的是，按下f5，看看会发生什么
and what I'm going to do now, well let's just hit f5 and see what happens
记住我们仍然有相同的投影矩阵，所以它看起来还是一样的
remember we still have the same projection matrix, so it still kind of looks the same
我的意思是它看起来被拉长了，因为我们改变了窗口的分辨率
I mean it looks stretched out, because we've changed the resolution of our window
但是投影矩阵保持不变
but kept the projection matrix the same
它不再是，我们的正方形不再是正方形，它是一个矩形
it's no longer, our square is no longer a square, it's kind of a rectangle
如果我们回到正交投影，我们在这个问题上做一些讨论
if we go back to our orthographic projection, let's play a little bit around with this
所以我要做的就是我之前提到的
so what I'm going to do is what I mentioned earlier
在我的例子中，它只是改变它在像素空间中，也就是1到1像素的映射
in my example, which is just changing it to be basically in pixel space, so 1 to 1 pixel mapping
要做到这一点，我将左边最边设为0，右边最边设为960
so to do that, I'm going to make 0 in my left most edge, 960 my right most edge
因为那是水平分辨率
because that's the horizontal resolution
下面是0，上面是540
I'm then going to make 0 in my bottom, and 540 in my top and
我想我得把它设为浮点数，因为这有点悲哀
I guess I will have to make this a float, because this is a bit sad
好了，酷，按f5，很好，所以什么都看不到
okay, cool, so let's hit f5, all right, cool, so we don't see anything at all
这是因为，我的意思是我们确实很难看到，因为当然
and that would be because, well I mean we do it's hard to see, because of course
如果我们在像素空间中，那么这个正方形是1×1像素
if we are in pixel space, then this square is 1 by 1 pixel
很明显只有一个像素，非常小，所以我们可以把它放大
which is obviously one pixel which is tiny, so what we can do is just boost this
所以我可以把它设为10.5，而不是0.5
so I might just set this to be like 10.5 instead of 0.5
这里加一个1，只是为了保持简单
I'll just add a 1 here just to keep it simple still
如果我们按f5，你现在可以看到它了
and if we hit f5, you can now kind of begin to see it
但它在左下角
but it's over here in the bottom left
因为我们所做的就是把底部做成像
because what we've done of course is we've made the bottom the like
(0,0)坐标在窗口的左下角
our (0,0) coordinate to be the bottom left of our window
如果我们向上滚动，我要做的就是重写这个
so if we scroll back up, what I'm going to do is just rewrite this
我只是想修改一下，但是我们重写一下，让这个是100x
I was just going to modify it, but let's just rewrite it, let's make this 100 by well
我们从100x100开始
we'll start at 100 by 100
然后我想我们是逆时针的，看起来是顺时针的
and then I think we go anti clockwise, and looks like we are going clockwise
给我一点时间，好的，我们就写100x100
give me a second here, okay, cool, so we'll just say 100 by 100
然后逆时针向右走，所以是200x100
then we go anti clockwise to the right, so we'll say 200 by still 100
然后去掉这些0.5
and I'll just get rid of these 0.5
然后x是200，这里是100，然后这个变成200x200，好了
and then we'll say 200 again for x and 100 here, and then this will become 200 200, okay
如果我们现在按f5，有了这些新的坐标
so if we hit f5 now, with these new coordinates that we have here
我们应该在某处看到一个正方形，是的，我们看到了
we should see a square somewhere and yes we do
如果我回到我的着色器，把这个变成我们实际的纹理
and if I go back to my shader and I change this to be a to be our actual texture
然后你们可以看到我们得到了这个渲染
then you can see we get this rendering here
所以我们在这里所做的是，你们可以看到
so what we've done here is you can see that really
我们只是稍微处理了一下坐标系
we've just played with the coordinate system a little bit
我们改变了投影矩阵x在0到960之间，y在0到540之间
we've changed our projection matrix to be between 0 and 960 for x, 0 and 540 for y
所以本质上我们改变了
so essentially we've changed
我们根据窗口的分辨率把它改成了每像素
we've changed it to be per pixel based on out on the resolution of our window
正因为如此
and then because of that
我们需要调整几何图形的位置使其在那个空间中
we've had to adjust the positions of our geometry to actually be in that space
所以不是-0.5 0.5
so rather than be like -0.5 0.5
实际上，我们不得不把它们改大一点，比如101，200等等
we've actually had to change them to be something a bit bigger like 101,200 and all of that
因为现在我们重新定义了顶点位置的空间
because now we've redefined what space we actually define vertex positions in
但归根结底
but at the end of the day
这些顶点的位置与我们的矩阵相乘
what happens is these vertex positions get multiplied with our matrix
这就把它们变成了-0.5x0.5
and that is what converse them back into being -0.5 by 0.5
让我们看看另一个例子
let's take a look at another example
那么为了把这个弄得更清楚，这是100×100
so just to make this absolutely clear, we have this 100 by 100
我要做的就是保留我的proj矩阵
what I'm going to do is I'll keep my proj matrix
但我会创建一个glm::vec4 vp，也就是顶点位置
but I'll make a glm vec4 and I'll call this vp, vertex position
我在这里创建一个vec4，它的坐标是100 100，然后是0 1
and I'll just create a vec4 here, that has the coordinate 100 by 100 and then 0 1
好了，我们没有一个z坐标
okay, so we don't have a z coordinate
对于1和w，我们指定1
and for 1 and for w we're just going to specify 1
接下来我要做的是输入glm::vec4 result = proj*vp
what I'm going to do then is type in glm vec4 result equals proj times vp
所以实际上我自己在CPU上做乘法
so I'm actually doing that multiplication myself right here on the CPU
看看结果是什么，这样我们就能看到了
just to see what the result is, so that we can actually see
记住我说过的，我们现在要做的是
now remember what I said, what we're doing here is
这个proj矩阵应该取我们的坐标和顶点位置
this proj matrix is supposed to take our coordinate our vertex position
然后把它转换成-1到1之间的空间
and convert it into a space that is between -1 and 1
按下f5，看看这个
so if I hit f5 and I take a look at this
如果我们看一下实际的proj矩阵，它看起来有点疯狂
if we look at our actual proj matrix, it looks a bit wild
我的意思是，这是0，不管怎样，我们真的不需要看它
I mean this is like 0.00, whatever, we don't really need to look at that
我们的顶点位置会当然是100
our vertex position is of course a hundred
100 0 1，如果我按f10来做这个计算
a hundred zero and one, if I hit f10 here to do this calculation
看看我们的结果，现在可能有点难看出来
take a look at our result, now it might be a little bit hard to see
我可以判断它是否有效，但你们可以看到
I'll really tell if it's worked or not, but you can see that
x和y当然一直是0 w一直是1
the x and y is that of course was always 0 w has been a remain 1
但x和y从100变成了-0.79和-0.62
but x and y have changed from being 100 100 to -0.79 and -0.62
记住这两个值-0.79和-0.62，如果我们看看这个
if we go to, so remember those two values -0.79 and -0.62, if we look at this
我们看一下左下角最左边的坐标，这说得通，不就是这样的吗
and we take a look at the bottom left most coordinate, that kind of makes sense, doesn't it like this
如果我们改变映射不再使用投影矩阵，我们得到-1到1
if we were to change our mapping to not use the projection matrix anymore, and we had -1 to 1
你们可以把它想象成从中间到右边的70%的距离
you can kind of imagine this as being around 70% of the way to there from the middle right
所以它所做的就是把100×100变成了-1到1的空间
so what it's done clearly is it has converted our 100 by 100 to be in that -1 to 1 space
那就是投影在2D和3D中的作用
and that is what projection does in both 2D and 3D
所以换句话说，正交矩阵或透视矩阵
so in other words, orthographic or perspective
同样与2D或3D无关，这就是人们通常联想到的东西
again nothing to do with 2D or 3D, is just what people commonly associate them with
所以在透视矩阵和正交矩阵中，没有关系，结果是一样的
so in perspective and orthograph projecting, doesn't matter, the same thing happens
你们所做的一切就是告诉你们的电脑
all you're doing is you're telling your computer
如何从你们正在处理的空间转换
how to convert from whatever space you're currently dealing with
就是你们在-1到1的标准设备坐标空间中定义的一些东西
which is something that you define yourself to that -1 to 1 normalized device coordinate space
那就是所有在OpenGL中的投影
and that is all there is to projection in OpenGL
不管怎样，我希望你们喜欢这个视频，如果喜欢的话，可以点赞
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did, you can hit the like button
你们也可以访问patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持本系列
you can also help support this series by going over to patreon.com/TheCherno
让我知道你们对这些更典型的视频有什么看法
let me know what you think of these kind of more typical videos
一方面，我真的很喜欢制作它们，因为我认为
on one hand, I really like making them, because I think that
比如像我这样的人可能会感兴趣
like people like me probably would be interested to
我希望有人能像我今天这样简单地解释它
I wish like someone explained it as simple as I hopefully did here today
当我学习这些东西的时候
when I was learning this kind of stuff
但另一方面，我知道你们中有些人可能想在屏幕上看到更多的东西
but on the other hand, I know that some of you probably want to see more things on the screen
想要看到更多的进展，想要得到有趣的东西
and want to see more progress, and want to get to the fun stuff
所以请告诉我你们的想法，如果你们对这个还Ok的话
so let me know what your thoughts are on this, if you're okay with this
如果你们想让我做一些更实际的事情，也许以后再回来讲理论
if you want me to do more practical things, and maybe come back and do the theory later
但无论哪种方式
but either way
如果你们想支持这个系列，可以通过访问patreon.com/TheCherno
if you're gonna have support the series, by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
非常感谢所有让这些视频成为可能的赞助人
huge thank you to all the patrons who make these videos possible
没有你们，我们就不会在这里相遇
would not be here without you guys
所以非常感谢大家，下次见，拜
so thank you so much, I will see you guys next time, goodbye